Guide to the Vladimir and Véra Nabokov publishing correspondence, 1945-1977.
Nabokov, Vladimir and Véra publishing correspondence, 1945-1977
- Series V. Correspondence to and from Clairouin 1947-1977
  - Correspondence to and from Clairouin, October 27, 1961 to November 21, 1961. (Box 7, Folder 31)
    11 TL, in French, to VN (1), VéN (8), Pierre Moxhet (1), from René Algrin (1). Mostly re the pirated Mexican edition of Laughter in the Dark and the pirated Lebanese editions of Lolita, the film version of Laughter, Gallimard's proposed paperback edition of Lolita, as well as various contractual and financial matters. Ergaz describes some books she is sending to the Nabokovs.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, November 22, 1961 to January 5, 1962. (Box 7, Folder 32)
    8 TL, in French, to VN (1) and VéN (7), with 5 autograph sheets of calculations. Mostly regarding the contract with Gallimard for Sebastian Knight, Gallimard's planned publication of The Defense before Pnin, various foreign contracts for Lolita, and the ongoing dispute with Olympia.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, January 17, 1962 to February 26, 1962. (Box 7, Folder 33)
    13 TL, in French, to VN (2) and VéN (11), regarding the revision of the French translation of The Defense, potential translators for Pale Fire (VN's new book), Serge Gainsbourg's request for permission to use extracts from Lolita as text for his songs, the contract with Gallimard for Sebastian Knight, the film versions of Lolita (to appear in the summer of 1962) and Laughter in the Dark (as yet not begun). Ergaz expresses disappointment that Véra has not enjoyed Le sang du ciel.
  - Correspondence to and from Clairouin, February 28, 1962 to March 30, 1962. (Box 7, Folder 34)
    11 TL, in French, to VéN (9) and René Algrin (1), and from René Algrin. Mostly regarding the proposed revision of Priel's translation of The Defense, VN's corrections for Chrestien's translation of Pnin, the film adaptation of Laughter in the Dark, legal proceedings in Lebanon, difficulties with New Directions over Gallimard's reissue of Sebastian Knight, the Vogue's illicit use of Lolita, and resolution of dispute with Olympia.
  - Correspondence to and from Clairouin, April 4, 1962 to May 9, 1962. (Box 7, Folder 35)
    13 TL, in French, English, and German, to VéN (8), René Algrin (1), Horst Tappe (1), l'Hôtel Continental (1), Weidenfeld and Nicolson (1), and from Horst Tappe (1). Mostly regarding the film adaptation of Laughter in the Dark, the publication of Pale Fire, contract difficulties with New Directions and Gallimard over The Defense, financial matters arising out of the resolution of the Olympia affair, Tappe's photograph portraits of VN, and the Indian publication of Lolita.
  - Correspondence to and from Clairouin, May 10, 1962 to June 23, 1962. (Box 7, Folder 36)
    8 TL, in French, English, and German, to VéN (5), from René Algrin (1), from Playboy to Ergaz (1) with copy of a letter sent by Playboy to VN requesting an article on Brigitte Bardot, the copy of a letter sent from Playboy to VN (1) with copy of a letter from Véra to Playboy politely declining the latter's offer of publication, and a postcard from Horst Tappe. Other letters discuss the contract situation re Sebastian Knight, the legal proceedings in Lebanon, and the film adaptation of Laughter.
  - Correspondence to and from Clairouin, June 27, 1962 to August 11, 1962. (Box 7, Folder 37)
    17 TL, in French, to the Nabokovs (2), VéN (8), René Algrin (2), and from Algrin (5). Deals with the Lebanese pirated editions, film adaptation of Laughter, foreign publication of Lolita, contract with Gallimard for Pale Fire (currently on American bestseller lists), publication of extracts of Pnin in the journal Arts, and contract difficulties with New Directions over Sebastian Knight.
  - Correspondence to and from Clairouin, August 16, 1962 to September 21, 1962. (Box 7, Folder 38)
    12 TL, in French and German, to VéN (8), René Algrin (1), Horst Tappe (1) with attached postcard from Tappe, from René Algrin (1), 1 autograph record of telephone conversation with Véra, and 1 list of all foreign contracts for Lolita. Discusses various contractual and financial matters, especially the contract with Gallimard for Pale Fire, and publication of Pnin in La revue de Paris (the first installment to be released at the same time as Gallimard's edition of the same).
  - Correspondence to and from Clairouin, October 5, 1962 to December 31, 1962. (Box 7, Folder 39)
    17 TL, in French, to VéN (16) and from René Algrin. Mostly regarding the publication and translation of Pale Fire, the film adaptation of Laughter in the Dark, and other contractual matters (mostly relating to foreign publication of Lolita).
  - Correspondence to and from Clairouin, January 1963 to February 14, 1963. (Box 7, Folder 40)
    11 TL, in French and English, to VN(1), VéN (8), René Algrin (1), from René Algrin (1), 1 copy of telegram sent to VN, and 1 autograph calculation. Mostly regarding the film adaptation of Laughter in the Dark (about which the Nabokovs are anxious), the search for a translator for Pale Fire, Ergaz's opinion of the film Lolita, and various financial matters re the foreign publication of Lolita.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, February 22, 1963 to April 30, 1963. (Box 7, Folder 41)
    11 TL, in French, to VéN (10) and René Algrin (1), with 1 autograph note. Primarily regarding the film adaptation of Laughter in the Dark, and the search for a translator for Pale Fire (finally settled on Girard, who, rather to the surprised amusement of Ergaz and Michel Mohrt, is a Canadian, and Coindreau, Faulkner's translator), as well as various financial matters re the foreign publication of Lolita.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, May 1963 to July 25, 1963. (Box 7, Folder 42)
    11 TL, in French, to VéN, with 1 autograph note. Provides more information about Raymond Girard, who, as VN had suggested (to the contemptuous amusement of Ergaz and Mohrt), is a bilingual Canadian, and discusses Lumbroso situation, attempts to place various stories, and contractual matters relating to Lolita and Sebastian Knight
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, July 29, 1963 to September 26, 1963. (Box 7, Folder 43)
    12 TL, in French and English, to VéN (11) and Claude Gallimard (1), with 1 autograph note, 1 statement, and copy of telegram sent to VN. Mostly regarding proposed Turkish edition of Lolita and other financial matters relating to foreign publication of that novel, contract dispute with New Directions, and Cannacs' revision of The Defense
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, October 10, 1963 to February 4, 1964. (Box 7, Folder 44)
    12 TL, in French, to VN (2), VéN (9), and René Algrin (1). Mostly regarding the Lumbrosos' situation, the contract dispute with New Directions, various contractual and financial matters re the foreign publication of Lolita (especially in Turkey), the translation of Pale Fire and the revision of The Defense translation.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, February 17, 1964 to May 13, 1964. (Box 7, Folder 45)
    17 TL, in French, to VN (3), VéN (8), René Algrin (1), the Hôtel Meurice (1) making reservations for the Nabkkovs, from René Algrin (3) and the Hôtel Meurice (1). Mostly re Gallimard's decision to publish The Gift, various contractual and financial matters relating to the foreign publication of Lolita, and the Girard/Coindreau translation of Pale Fire
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, May 16, 1964 to August 4, 1964. (Box 7, Folder 46)
    15 TL, in French, to VN (1) and VéN (14), 1 autograph note and 1 copy of a telegram sent to VN. Mostly concerning the contract with Gallimard for The Gift, the film adaptation of Laughter (there are now rumors that Truffaut will be signed to make the film), the possible publication of Eugene Onegin, and the proposed publication of Lolita in an anthology entitled Les chefs-d'oeuvre de l'erotisme (intended not to be pornographic).
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, August 25, 1964 to November 10, 1964. (Box 8, Folder 1)
    13 TL, to VN (1), VéN (8), René Algrin (2), and M. Macridès (1), from Renè Algrin (1), with a typed list outlining the foreign contracts for Lolita (dated 8.25.64 but updated until 12.4.64), 1 autograph note from a Mlle. Bunel (?), and an unsigned autograph note. Discusses pirated Greek and Lebanese editions of Lolita and other contractual matters, and new legal proceedings against Girodias.
  - Correspondence to and from Clairouin, November 17, 1964 to January 15, 1965. (Box 8, Folder 2)
    10 TL, in French to VéN (8) and Léonidas Cottakis (1), from Cottakis (1), with 3 sheets of autograph calculations, and 1 statement in Greek. Mostly re the pirated Greek edition of Lolita (Cottakis is the lawyer employed by Clairouin to take action against Gerolymbos and Dorikos), contractual matters re to the foreign publication of Lolita, and the translation of Pale Fire (the revisions to which Michel Mohrt hopes VN will complete quickly).
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, January 22, 1965 to March 15, 1965. (Box 8, Folder 3)
    13 TL, in French, to VN (2), VéN (9), Horst Tappe (1), Léonidas Cottakis (1). Mostly re the pirated Greek edition of Lolita, the transfer of film rights for Laughter in the Dark to Pierre Braunberger and Henri de Clarens (who speak of Truffaut as director), the search for a translator for The Gift (Ergaz has decided not to translate the novel herself because of illness), and publication of Pale Fire.
  - Correspondence to and from Clairouin, March 23, 1965 to June 9, 1965. (Box 8, Folder 4)
    14 TL, in French, to VéN (11), Cottakis (2), Algrin (1). Mostly regarding the pirated Greek and Lebanese editions of Lolita and Laughter in the Dark, various contractual and financial matters re the foreign publication of Lolita (especially an offer from a Yugoslavian firm), the translation of Pale Fire (to be undertaken by Girard), and VN's own translation of Lolita into Russian.
  - Correspondence to and from Clairouin, June 30, 1965 to September 27, 1965. (Box 8, Folder 5)
    10 TL, in French, to VéN (6), to Algrin (2), from Algrin (2). Outlines the publcation possibilities for VN's translation of Lolita into Russian, and discusses proofs of Pale Fire (to be published as early as the fall), and various contractual matters re the foreign publication of Lolita.
  - Correspondence to and from Clairouin, September 30, 1965 to November 24, 1965. (Box 8, Folder 6)
    12 TL, in French and English, to VN (1), VéN (7), Cottakis (1), John-Marie Jammes (1) and Novoe Russkoe Slove (1),1 from Gertrude Fehr (Swiss photographer). Mostly regarding the possible publication of The Eye, the publication of Lolita in Russian and other contractual and financial matters having to do with Lolita, the publication of Pale Fire, and the possible publication of the memoirs of Count Ignatieff (given to Ergaz by the current Canadian ambassador to NATO, George Ignatieff).
  - Correspondence to and from Clairouin, November 25, 1965 to December 17, 1965. (Box 8, Folder 7)
    12 TL, in French, to VéN (7), Algrin (1), Fehr (2), from Algrin (1), Fehr (1), typed summary of Cottakis' report on the pirated Greek editions of Lolita and Laughter in the Dark. Discusses the release of Pale Fire and Girard's translation of The Gift, and various contractual and financial matters having to do with the foreign publication of Lolita.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, December 21, 1965 to March 2, 1966. (Box 8, Folder 8)
    13 TL, in English and French, to VéN (11), Cottakis (1), and from Vitaly Komarow (1). Mostly regarding the publication of Lolita in Russian, as well as other contractual and financial matters having to do with the foreign publication of Lolita, Girard's translation of The Gift, and Gallimard's offer for The Eye (to be translated by Magnane).
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, March 4, 1966 to May 16, 1966. (Box 8, Folder 9)
    14 TL, in French, to VéN (13), to Vitaly Komarow (1). Mostly re the contract with Gallimard for The Eye, Gallimard's interest in Despair, Gallimard's publication of The Defense (about to be publishe serially in The New Yorker), a Czechoslovakian offer for Pale Fire, and various contractual and financial matters having to do with Lolita.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, May 23, 1966 to October 15, 1966. (Box 8, Folder 10)
    14 TL in French to VéN. Deals with various financial matters re Lolita (especially the Spanish edition, held up by censorship, and the many proposed Indian editions for Lolita. and also Laughter in the Dark). Notes also the possibility that the film rights to Laughter in the Dark may be free, and are being pursued by a Monsieur Mage. Also notes with pleasure the publication of Lolita in Russian.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, October 24, 1966 to January 23, 1967. (Box 8, Folder 11)
    11 TL in French to VéN, dealing with the eventual publication of The Eye and The Gift (both of which translations VN apparently approves), and contractual and financial matters having to do with the foreign publication of Lolita. Schébéko asks after the Russan edition of Lolita, and gives news of Ergaz, who undergoes an operation at this time.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, January 30, 1967 to September 21, 1967. (Box 8, Folder 12)
    14 TL in French to VéN, with 2 autograph notes. Concerning the translation and publication of The Eye, The Gift, Grasset's less than successful edition of Laughter in the Dark, various contractual and financial matters having to do with the foreign publication of Lolita, and enthusiastic reviews of VN's work in the Sunday Telegraph (England) and Le Monde (France). Notes with sadness Ergaz's slow progress into death, and then, following E.'s death, expresses regret that Véra's check for flowers (for Ergaz's funeral) should not have been cashed. Lists some additional stories that have appeared in print (in France).
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, September 25, 1967 to December 31, 1967. (Box 8, Folder 13)
    12 TL in French to VéN, with 2 autograph scraps. Mostly regarding various contractual and financial matters having to do with Lolita, VN's desire to leave Gallimard (because of the latter's failures on the publicity front), the publication of The Gift (including the list of errata that VN wants to see included), and several short stories.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, January 9, 1968 to June 19, 1968. (Box 8, Folder 14)
    12 TL, in French, to VN (1) and VéN (11), noting the annulation of the contract with Olympia, and the interest of les Editions du Chêne in buying the now available rights to Lolita. Also discusses possible Yugoslavian publishers for Lolita., as well as the possible publication of some of VN's short stories.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, June 20, 1968 to December 24, 1968. (Box 8, Folder 15)
    15 TL in French to VéN, regarding various contractual and financial matters having to do with the foreing publication of Lolita (especially in India and Yugoslavia), Gallimard's desire to publish King, Queen, Knave next, and new rumblings from Olympia.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, January 6, 1969 to May 22, 1969 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    12 TL in French to VéN, with 1 autograph calculation. Mostly re Czech and Yugoslavian editions of Lolita, and Czech and Swiss publication of VN's short stories, as well as contract with Gallimard for King, Queen, Knave and publicity for The Eye and The Gift. Notes Girodias is appealing the last verdict.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, May 28, 1969 to September 25, 1969. (Box 8, Folder 17)
    15 TL in French to VéN, with 3 autograph records of telephone conversations. Mostly re: various contractual matters with Lolita, Gallimard's readiness to publish collection of VN's stories, and their reluctance to sign a contract for Ada based on VN's stipulations.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, October 14, 1969 to December 30, 1969. (Box 8, Folder 18)
    13 TL in French to VéN, re: the contract with Fayard for Ada, and Spanish edition of Lolita.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, January 6, 1970 to April 22, 1970. (Box 8, Folder 19)
    10 TL in French to VéN, with 1 typed list of VN's works published in Russian, English and French, and 1 autograph calculation. Mostly regarding various foreign contracts for Lolita (in Iceland, Greece, Yugoslavia, Czechoslovakia, and asking for reimbursement of the legal costs incurred in the appeals case against Olympia.
  - Correspondence to and from Clairouin, May 20, 1970 to December 29, 1970. (Box 8, Folder 20)
    15 TL in French to VéN (12), Jean-Jacques Celly (1), and from Celly (1) and the Icelandic agent Sveinbjorn Jonsson (1). Regarding the American and French publications (by McGraw-Hill and Fayard) of Mary, Fayard's publication of Ada, and various foreign contracts for Lolita. The correspondence with Celly (who is with Vanderbilt University in France) seems to concern a study Celly is undertaking, and for which he would like a copy of The Defense.
  - Correspondence to and from Clairouin, January 6, 1971 to May 12, 1971. (Box 8, Folder 21)
    13 TL, in French, to VéN(11) and P. Daguerressar (1), and from Daguerressar to Gallimard (forwarded to Clairouin), with 1 autograph note. Regarding Fayard's publication of Mary, various foreign contracts for Lolita, the possibility of reacquiring Grasset's largely unsuccessful edition of Laughter in the Dark, and an offer from Librairie générale française to publish many of VN's works in paperback form. Correspondence with Daguerressar about the latter's offer to translate Ada, which unfortunately has already been translated and is about to be published.
  - Correspondence to and from Clairouin, May 17, 1971 to September 8, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    13 TL, in French, to VéN (11), Gallimard (1), from Librairie générale française (1), with 1 autograph record of telephone conversation. Mostly regarding various foreign contracts for Lolita, the translation of Ada, a request from a Lily Powell for the names of VN's German translators, and the contract with L.G.F. for paperback editions of a number of VN's works, a contract that will incite Gallimard to legal action ("c'est la guerre").
  - Correspondence to and from Clairouin, September 27, 1971 to November 26, 1971. (Box 8, Folder 23)
    14 TL, in French, to VéN (11) and Jacques Mercier (1), from Gallimard (2), with 1 typed list of Ada's various editions, and 1 autograph record of a telephone conversation. Mostly concerning the contract mess with Gallimard, Grasset, and Fayard, as well as various foreign contracts for Lolita, and the slow pace of the Ada translation. Shébéko asks Mercier for his help in the contract dispute with Gallimard.
  - Correspondence to and from Clairouin, December 3, 1971 to March 8, 1972. (Box 8, Folder 24)
    12 TL, in French, to VéN (9), to Livre de Poche from Livre de Poche (2; 1 to Clairouin, and 1 to VN), with 1 typed list of documents sent Mercier. Mostly regarding various foreign contracts for Lolita, the continuing dispute between Livre de Poche and Gallimard/Folio, the publication of King, Queen, Knave, and a series of interviews for "France-Culture." Includes original envelope for de Fallois' (for Livre de Poche) letter of 3.2.72.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, March 11, 1972 to March 15, 1972. (Box 8, Folder 25)
    3 TL, in French, to VéN (1) and Gallimard (2), with 4 autograph fragments (notes, calculations). The letters to Gallimard (one final version, plus a series of photocopied drafts approved by the Nabokovs; probably drafted by Mercier) state VN's position re: publication of Lolita in paperback form.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, March 16, 1972 to April 12, 1972. (Box 8, Folder 26)
    6 TL, in French, to VéN (4), from Gallimard (2, one of which is a photocopy). The letters from Gallimard outline the firm's position on the paperback editions of VN's works (needless to say, they refuse to cede the rights to Livre de Poche). While Schébéko believes VN might win a court decision forcing Gallimard to cede the paperback rights for Lolita, it is likely Gallimard would retain the rights to other works by VN, and refuse to publish them in any form.
  - Correspondence to and from Clairouin, April 25, 1972 to September 20, 1972. (Box 8, Folder 27)
    12 TL, in French and English, to VéN (8), from Gallimard (4), one of which is a photocopy). Mostly regarding the contract with Gallimard/Folio for the paperback editions of Lolita, Despair, and 3 others (Pnin and The Defense, though not Sebastian Knight, as the "absurd" impasse with New Directions continues), as well as the Ada translation (despite the slow pace, VN will not, as Schébéko suggests, allow Mary to appear before Ada). Includes typed copy of the blurb that will appear on the back of Lolita (the opening of Lolita and a short biographical note). Notes with delight that VN has finished another novel (Transparent Things).
  - Correspondence to and from Clairouin, September 27, 1972 to November 29, 1972. (Box 8, Folder 28)
    8 TL, in French, to VéN (5) and Gallimard (1), from Gallimard (2), with autograph calculations. Mostly re: the contracts with Gallimard/Folio for paperback editions of Lolita, Pnin, The Defense, and Despair. Also contract matters re foreign editions of Lolita.
  - Correspondence to and from Clairouin, December 13, 1972 to March 13, 1973. (Box 8, Folder 29)
    12 TL, in French and English, to VéN (5), Gallimard (4), and Joan Daly (for the Literary Trust), from Gallimard (2), with 1 typed list detailing VN's royalties. Dealing with the contract with Gallimard (VN is somewhat displeased with the terms and their ambiguous wording, but Schébéko urges him to sign) and publication details (asking VN to approve book jackets, for example). Notes slow pace of Ada translation, and Fayard's concern that VN will sell Transparent Things to another publisher (he will not show it to Fayard until the Ada translation is completed). Includes a personal note from Schébéko commiserating with Véra over her back (an especially unfortunate circumstance, writes Schébéko, given the perfection of Véra's posture), and offering some advice.
  - Correspondence to and from Clairouin, March 22, 1973 to May 16, 1973. (Box 8, Folder 30)
    12 TL, in French, to VéN (6), Gallimard (4), from Gallimard (1) and from Gallimard to VéN (1, this a copy sent to Schébéko explaining some financial matters) with 1 autograph note. Mostly regarding Gallimard/Folio's paperback editions of Pnin, Lolita and Despair, as well as the Chahine translation of Ada. Includes a more personal note from Schébéko detailing a recent meeting with their mutual friend Madame Tarr.
  - Correspondence to and from Clairouin, May 25, 1973 to September 3, 1973. (Box 8, Folder 31)
    14 TL, in French and English, to VéN (12), Garlick & Hoffman (1), and from Garlick and Hoffman (1). Mostly re: foreign editions of Lolita, financial matters re Gallimard, French taxes, and excruciating pace of the Ada translation (still only half completed by September 3).
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, September 11, 1973 to January 18, 1974. (Box 8, Folder 32)
    11 TL, in French and English, to VéN with 1 bill for flowers sent to the Nabokovs, and 2 autograph notes. Mostly regarding foreign editions of Lolita, a copy of the Russian translation of Lolita sent by the Nabokovs for Siniavsky, the contract with Fayard for Transparent Things (to be translated by Donald Harper, and published simultaneously with Ada, which still lacks 200 pages in the translation), Grasset's paperback edition of Laughter in the Dark, and financial matters re Gallimard.
  - Correspondence to and from Clairouin, January 29, 1974 to May 7, 1974. (Box 8, Folder 33)